A Guide to the Frank Loucks Hereford, Jr. Papers
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Frank Loucks Hereford Jr. Collection
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
12764-a
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquistion Information
The collection was transferred from the Office of the Vice-President and Provost to Special Collections Library on August 12, 1981.
Biographical/Historical Information
Frank Loucks Hereford Jr. was born in Lake Charles, Louisiana on July 18, 1923. He received a B. A. at the University of Virginia in 1943 and a Ph.D. in Physics at the University in 1947. While an undergraduate, he wrote a sports column for the University newspaper, College Topics. He was a research scientist in the United States Navy from 1942 to 1945. During the war years he worked on research for the Manhattan Project under Dr. Jesse Beams, who called him "one of the best all around physicists with whom I have ever been associated." He worked for the Bartol Research Foundation at Swarthmore College in Pennsylvania from 1947 to 1949. He married Ann Lane in 1948 and became an Associate Professor of Physics at the University of Virginia in 1949, rising to full professor in 1952, and Dean of the Graduate School of Arts and Sciences in 1962. He was named the Robert C. Taylor Professor of Physics in 1966 and was promoted to Provost of the University, the chief academic officer after the President. Also in 1966 he received the Thomas Jefferson Award in recognition of his extensive services in teaching, research and administration. In 1970 he was Provost and Vice-President, being the first occupant of this position. Throughout his career, Mr. Hereford was noted as an able teacher and an articulate advocate of improving the quality of education at the University. He guided and planned for the growth of the University and formulated plans for the admission of women to the College of Arts and Sciences. He was visiting professor at the University of St. Andrews, Scotland from 1971 to 1972. He was inaugurated as the fifth president of the University of Virginia in 1974. He was the recipient of the Raven Award in 1983, the Algernon Sydney Sullivan Award in 1985, as well as the IMP Society Distinguished Faculty Award in the same year. He was a member of many honor societies including Phi Beta Kappa, Omicron Delta Kappa, Alpha Tau Omega, Raven Society, Sigma XI, and Fellow of American Physical Society. He was on the Board of Directors of the Virginia National Bank, Belfield School; St. Anne's School; Woodberry Forest School; The Mariners Museum and Gould, Inc. He was the author of numerous publications and was an avid sportsman, enjoying hunting and tennis as well as spectator sports.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of the personal papers (1973-1985) of the University of Virginia's fifth president, Frank Loucks Hereford, Jr. The collection is 708 items, 3 Hollinger Boxes and 1.25 linear feet. Included in the collection is personal correspondence of President Hereford, which is mostly thank you letters, including one to the Seven Society and a resolution from the Board of Visitors in his honor.
There is some correspondence about conflicts of interest policies as President of the University. There is also information about Carrs Hill. Of particular interest in the correspondence, is a letter from John A. Gill to the president that is filled with racism against African Americans and Jews at the University of Virginia and Farmington Hunt Club. The letter was written to President Hereford after the president had made a statement in favor of more diversity at the University and Farmington.
There is also information about President Hereford's inauguration in 1974 and his resignation after eleven years in 1984, as well as Board of Visitors meeting minutes. There are also original speeches of the President from 1973 to 1985, including materials that he used to prepare his speeches. Included with the University of Virginia related speech materials are articles about the history of the University and correspondence between President Hereford and former alumni who reminisced about the early days at the University. There are also "Remarks by Walter Dexter Whitehead and a typescript of a "Papraphrased Conversation between Hereford and Richard M. Brandt." In the University of Virginia miscellaneous there is a poem by Raymond C. Bice written for President Hereford's birthday. Correspondents of the President include Governor Mills E. Godwin, Jr.; Thomas J. Michie, Jr.; Francis L. Berkeley, Jr.; Walter Muir Whitehill; J. C. Smiddy; Frank S. Walker; Edgar and Eleanor Shannon, Jr.; Thomas A. Graves; Dumas Malone; Joseph H. McConnell; Charles L. Brown; and Gilbert "Gilly" J. Sullivan.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically by topic and chronologically within each folder.
Contents List
- 1974; 1979; 1983 Correspondence about Carr's Hill, 14 items (Box-folder 1:1)
  There are thank you letters for gifts to Carr's Hill, information about items on loan, and budget information on entertaining
- 1974-1984 Correspondence about Conflicts of Interest, 11 items (Box-folder 1:2)
  Included are policies on conflict of interest and correspondence from President Hereford clarifying that he was not profiting from his son's businesses while they provided service to the University. There are also letters to Myron E. Tremain and Bernard J. Haggerty about resigning from the board of Virginia National Bank due to conflicts of interest.
- 1974 October 9 John A. Gill to Frank Hereford, 1 item (Box-folder 1:3)
  There is a letter from John A. Gill with very strong and discriminating language against Negroes and Jews attending the University of Virginia and Farmington Hunt Club. Gill was upset that President Hereford had made a statement about changing the policies at Farmington to include all people and Gill was begging Hereford to stand against this "liberal" position.
- 1973-1975; 1976 Correspondence of Frank Hereford, 69 items (Box-folder 1:4)
  Included is Hereford's letter of resignation as professor of physics, notes for his Board of Visitors infoview, and letters of congratulations from Hereford to Mills E. Godwin, Jr. and Thomas J. Michie, Jr. on their successful elections. Hereford also corresponded with Walter Muir Whitehill, and Francis L. Berkeley, Jr. about plans for the Rotunda. There are also newspaper clippings about President Hereford's inauguration. Other correspondents include J. C. Smiddy, Frank S. Walker, Edgar F. Shannon, Jr., and Thomas A. Graves.
- 1979-1981 Correspondence of Frank Hereford, 76 items (Box-folder 1:5)
  Included is a letter to Associate Justice of the U. S. Supreme Court, Lewis J. Powell, Jr. about a hunting trip. There are mostly thank you letters from the President and his wife. There is also a letter to Hereford from the Board of Visitors about receiving a salary increase. There are also letters about the death of his daughter, Molly, in a tragic car accident, including a letter from Paul Gaston.
- 1982-1984 Correspondence of Frank Hereford, 96 items (Box-folder 1:6)
  There are mostly friendly inquiries and thank you letters. Included are letters about receiving the 1983 Raven Award. Correspondents include Robert M. Gooch, Gilbert J. Sullivan, and William H. Fishback.
- 1985 Correspondence of Frank Hereford, 13 items (Box-folder 1:7)
  There are thank you letters from Hereford for an evening held for him at Carr's Hill and a thank you letter to the Seven Society. Included is a resolution from the Board of Visitors honoring Hereford. There are also nominations for him to serve on the National Science board.
- n. d. Miscellaneous notes, 2 items (Box-folder 1:8)
  Handwritten notes by President Hereford which seem to make up a checklist of items needing his attention
- n. d. Miscellaneous physics paper, 1 item (Box-folder 1:9)
- 1984-1985 Resignation, 10 items (Box-folder 1:10)
  There are newspaper clippings, Board of Visitors meeting minutes, and correspondence about President Hereford's resignation after eleven years as president, including letters from Dumas Malone, Eleanor Shannon, Joseph H. McConnell, Charles L. Brown, and Thomas A. Graves.
- n. d. Resume, 11 items (Box-folder 1:11)
  Included are several vitas of President Hereford as well as visa applications to Japan
- 1977-1982 Rotunda, 2 items (Box-folder 1:12)
  There is information about names for the Rotunda Blocks. There is also information about the Pep Band performing at the Rotunda for the Lawn Society Banquet.
- n. d. Speech list, 1 item (Box-folder 2:1)
  There is a list of speeches made by President Hereford
- 1974 Speeches, 19 items (Box-folder 2:2)
  Speeches include Richmond Rotary Club; Arthur J. Morris Law Library; Faculty Wives; Chamber of Commerce; Diabetes-Endocrinology Center; Forum club; Inaugural address; Graduate Business School Sponsors; New Faculty Members; Entering Students; Resident Staff; Jaycees; Commencement Address for Florida Institute of Technology; Woodberry Forest; Hampden-Sydney College; Associates of the University Library; and Clinch Valley.
- 1975 Speeches, 24 items (Box-folder 2:3)
  Speeches include Virginia Club of Washington; Entering Students; Southern Surgical Association; Center for Oceans Law & Policy; New Faculty Members; Governor and Budget Advisory Committee; Dedication of the Darden School; Resident Staff; Charlottesville Rotary Club; Virginia Bankers Association; Final Exercises; Service Award Ceremony; Law Day Luncheon; Dr. Wade Hampton Frost Professorship; Founders Day; Thomas Jefferson Society Alumni; Board of Managers of Alumni Association; Associates of the Library; Notes for the Crystallographers; Federal Executive Institute Seminar; Association of Virginia Colleges Annual Meeting; and Chairs Dinner.
- 1976 Speeches, 19 items (Box-folder 2:4)
  Speeches include School of Education; State of the University; Fall Convocation; New Faculty Members; Entering Students; Resident Staff; Conferring Law Degrees; Final Exercises; Rotunda Dedication; Founders Day; 1926 Graduates; Omicron Delta Kappa; and Alumni
- 1977 Speeches, 17 items (Box-folder 2:5)
  Speeches include Medical Alumni Board; Fall Convocation; Lawn Society; Introduction of Governor Godwin; New Faculty Members; Resident Staff; 1952 Class Reunion; Final Exercises; Chairs Dinner; Thomas Jefferson Society; Founders Day; Alumni; Omicron Delta Kappa; Medical Advisory Committee; and Entering Students
- 1978 Speeches, 20 items (Box-folder 2:6)
  Speeches include Congressional Delegation; Federal Executive Institute; Winchester Rotary Club; New Faculty Members; Entering Students; Local Government Officers; Final Exercises; Alumni Awards Dinner; Founders Day; Omicron Delta Kappa; Faculty Bicentennial Speaker Series about Women; Thomas Jefferson Society; Norfolk Rotary Club; Panama Canal Treaties Symposium; Appropriations Committee of the House of Delegates; Fall Convocation and Lawn Society
- 1979-1980 Speeches, 36 items (Box-folder 2:7)
  Speeches include New York Alumni; Lynchburg Alumni; Philadelphia Alumni; Alumni Awards Dinner; Dedication of Sponsors Hall; Fall Convocation; New Faculty Members; Entering Students; New Student Convocation; Resident Staff; Local Government Officials Conference; Final Exercises; Sidney S. Negus Memorial Symposium; Dumas Malone Ceremony; Dedication of Walter L. Brown; Law Class Reunion Dinner (Senator Edward Kennedy) Thomas Jefferson Society; Founders Day; Chairs Dinner; Easters; Faculty Bicentennial Speaker Series; Dedication of Shannon Garden; Parents Day; Alumni State of the University; Medical Alumni Association; and General Professional Advisory Committee.
- 1981-1982 Speeches, 38 items (Box-folder 3:1)
  Speeches include Parent's Committee; Alumni Homecoming; Fall Convocation; Darden Convocation; New Student Convocation; Founders Day; New Faculty Members; Student Aid Foundation; Resident Staff; Science Engineering and Applied Sciences Conferring Degrees; State of the University Address; Thomas Jefferson Society; University Union; Prospects For Higher Education; Medical Alumni Advisory Committee; W. Ralph Singleton; Local Government Officials Conference; Final Exercises; Columbia Alumni; Charleston Alumni; Memphis Alumni; Charlottesville Rotary Club; and the Clemons Library Dedication.
- 1983-1984 Speeches, 25 items (Box-folder 3:2)
  Speeches include Parents Day; Fall Convocation; New Faculty Members; Entering Students; Darden School Sponsors; New Student Convocation; Final Exercises; Thomas Jefferson Society; Omicron Delta Kappa; Founders Day; Baltimore Area Campaign Kick-Off; Roanoke Area Campaign Kick-Off; Wilmington Area Kick-Off; New York Area Campaign Kick-Off; Lynchburg Campaign Kick-Off; Chattanooga Alumni; Atlanta Alumni; Houston Alumni; New Orleans Alumni; Maryland Alumni; Budget Requests; SCHE Conference; Groundbreaking of Replacement Hospital; Introduction of John Casteen; and Lawn Advisory Board.
- 1985 Speeches, 4 items (Box-folder 3:3)
  Speeches were addressed to the UVA Women Faculty; Founders Day attendees; Clifton Waller Barrett Dinner guests, and Final Exercises
- 1967-1973 Speeches Before Hereford was President, 13 items (Box-folder 3:4)
- 1925-1979; n. d. Speech material, 57 items (Box-folder 3:5)
  There are articles, and reference materials for speeches. The material is divided into different subject areas such as earlier alumni speeches; enrollment; financial information; historical facts; honor system; medical school; miscellaneous; and public vs. private Institutions.
- 1893; 1921-1922; 1965-1984; n. d. Speech material: UVA related materials, 32 items (Box-folder 3:6)
  There is information pertaining to the history of the University of Virginia that Hereford used in his speeches. Included are photocopies from Philip Bruce's, "History of the University of Virginia," an article by John Hammond Moore, "Morgan Robinson Preservation of the Traditions of the University of Virginia," an article, "Another Peppercorn for Mr. Jefferson," and an article from the Magazine of Albemarle County History, "Lafayette in Albemarle." There are copies of Board of Visitors minutes from 1909; a report from the UVA Faculty Committee denying the admission of Women (1893;) "Remarks by Walter Dexter Whitehead, Dean of the Faculty of Arts and Science" (1971 December 14); "Remarks by Mills Godwin" at President Hereford's inauguration; and a typescript manuscript of a "Paraphrased Conversation between Richard M. Brandt and President Hereford (April 19,1973)
- 1975-1984; n. d. University of Virginia miscellaneous, 10 items (Box-folder 3:7)
  There is a poem by Raymond C. Bice written for President Hereford's birthday; poems by Frank L. Hereford, Jr., endowment figures, Virginia Freedom for Information legislation, and lists of tenured faculty and members of the standing committees of the Board of Visitors.